In space no one can hear you scream.
Alien is a horror, science fiction film directed by Ridley Scott.
During its return to the earth, commercial spaceship Nostromo
intercepts a distress signal from a distant planet.
When a three-member team of the crew discovers a chamber containing thousands of eggs
on the planet, a creature inside one of the eggs attacks an explorer.
The entire crew is unaware of the impending nightmare set to descend upon them when
the alien parasite planted inside its unfortunate host is birthed.
Dallas, played by Tom Skerritt.
Ripley, played by Sigourney Weaver.
Lambert, played by Veronica Cartwright.
Brett, played by Harry Dean Stanton.
Kane, played by John Hurt.
Ash, played by Ian Holm.
Alien is a 1979 science fiction horror film directed by Ridley Scott and written
by Dan O'Bannon, based on a story by O'Bannon and Ronald Shusett.
It follows a commercial starship crew who investigate a derelict space
vessel and are hunted by a deadly extraterrestrial creature.
The film stars Tom Skerritt, Sigourney Weaver, Veronica Cartwright,
Harry Dean Stanton, John Hurt, Ian Holm, and Yaphet Kotto.
It was produced by Gordon Carroll, David Giler, and Walter Hill through their
company Brandywine Productions and was distributed by 20th Century-Fox.
Giler and Hill revised and made additions to the
script; Shusett was the executive producer.
The alien creatures and environments were designed by the Swiss artist H.
Giger, while the concept artists Ron Cobb and
Chris Foss designed the other sets.
Alien premiered on May 25, 1979, the opening night of the
fourth Seattle International Film Festival.
It received a wide release on June 22 and was released
on September 6 in the United Kingdom.
It initially received mixed reviews, but won the Academy Award for Best Visual Effects, three Saturn Awards (Best Science Fiction Film,
Best Direction for Scott, and Best Supporting Actress for Cartwright), and a Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation.
Alien grossed $78.9 million in the United States and £7.8 million in
the United Kingdom during its first theatrical run.
Its worldwide gross has been estimated at between $104 million and $188 million.
In subsequent years, Alien was critically reassessed and is now considered one of the
greatest and most influential science fiction and horror films of all time.
In 2002, Alien was deemed "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant" by the Library of
Congress and was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry.
In 2008, it was ranked by the American Film Institute as the seventh-best film in the
science fiction genre, and as the 33rd-greatest film of all time by Empire.
The success of Alien spawned a media franchise of films, books, video
games, and toys, and propelled Weaver's acting career.
The story of her character's encounters with the alien creatures became the thematic and narrative
core of the sequels Aliens (1986), Alien 3 (1992), and Alien Resurrection (1997).
A crossover with the Predator franchise produced the Alien vs.
Predator films, while a two-film prequel series was directed by Scott before
Alien: Romulus (2024), a standalone sequel, was released.
A television prequel written by Noah Hawley and produced by Scott,
Alien: Earth, was released on FX on Hulu on August 12, 2025.
The film explores themes of android, spacecraft,
space marine, biology, dystopia.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking.